A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, S-Z FA394
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Walker, Sydnor H., 0.2 Cubic Feet 1 half-letter document box and 1 microfilm box
  Upon her return to the U.S. in 1924, Walker was recruited by Ruml to work for the LSRM as a research associate. She was a staunch advocate of using scientific and standardized methods to conduct research in the social sciences. While working for the LSRM, Walker continued her studies at Columbia University, receiving her Ph.D. in economics in 1928. Her dissertation, "Social Work and the Training of Social Workers," was published by the University of North Carolina Press in 1928.
  When many of LSRM's programs were consolidated with the RF in 1929 and a new Division of the Social Sciences created, Walker became Assistant Director of the division. She was promoted to Associate Director in 1933 and Acting Director in 1937. Among her interests at the RF, she was a proponent of improving the teaching of social work and the administration of social welfare programs. Her grant-making extended to many southern universities. She also contributed to the development of the social sciences outside the U.S., working with grantees in Europe and Latin America.
  Resigning from the RF in 1943 for health reasons, she worked on a report for the Woodrow Wilson Foundation, "The First Hundred Days of the Atomic Age," which was published in 1945.
  She served as a trustee for Vassar College from 1939-1943 and was appointed assistant to the president of Vassar College in 1948, a position she held until 1957.
  Sydnor H. Walker passed away in 1966.
  [1] Josephine Gleason et al. "Sydnor Harrison Walker: A Memorial Minute," Vassar Faculty Meeting, December 1966, Biographical Files Collection, Vassar College Archives, Vassar Libraries.
  - Appendix, 1925-1926; Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 1, Box 489)
    This Appendix lists the dates, institutions, and names of individuals interviewed by Miss Walker between 1925 and 1926.
  - 1925 October-December, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 8)
    This diary is record of Ms. Walker's meetings with university administrators, social science researchers, and social workers. The diary reveals some of the social science research and innovation that was underway in the United States that was being supported by the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial. The last part of the document describes the proper qualities and training necessary for a social worker as described by the Association of Schools of Professional Social Work.
    Social sciences; United States
  - 1926, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 56)
    This diary is a record of Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews with social science researchers and social work experts between January 12 and December 17, 1926. The document reveals Ms. Walker's travels around the country to keep tabs on the projects and innovations in social science taking place in the top universities and institutions for social work and sociology. Her diary gives a status report on some of the largest social science projects across the country as well as the planned expansion of institutions and university programs to continue their work.
  - 1927, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 173)
    This diary is a record of Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews with social science researchers and social work experts between January 24 and December 21, 1927. The document reveals Ms. Walker's travels around the country to keep tabs on the projects and innovations in social science taking place in the top universities and institutions for social work and sociology. Her diary gives a status report on some of the largest social science projects across the country as well as the planned expansion of institutions and university programs to continue their work.
  - 1928, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 270)
    This diary is a record of Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews with social science researchers and social work experts between January 3 and December 14, 1928. The diary records Ms. Walker's travel both within the United States to various universities and social science institutions, as well as a trip to Europe from May 15 through June 9 to visit the modern social science bureaus and university training and research programs. Ms. Walker's destinations in Europe included London, Oxford, Birmingham, Manchester, Liverpool, Edinburgh, Paris, Amsterdam, and Stockholm. Ms. Walker kept a record of her impressions of the calibre and status of social science research and progress in social work both in the United States and abroad over the course of her diary, and her impressions of individual researchers are also recorded.
    Sweden; United States; Holland (Netherlands: Province); Social sciences; England; France
  - Index, 1929-1937; Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 378)
    Index to all diaries between 1929-1937; 7 pages.
  - 1929, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 385, Box 489)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between February 4 and December 9, 1929 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States, as well as mentioning programs underway in Europe and China with Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1930, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 435, Box 489)
    This brief diary contains Ms. Walker's notes from interviews with professors and administrators at several top schools and institutes for social work in the United States, dating between January 18 and September 12, 1930. Ms. Walker's provides the requests from the individuals seeking grant support from the Rockefeller Foundation as well as her professional recommendations concerning the schools and personnel involved. Walker includes details about the types of projects being pursued and the level of support they are already receiving.
  - 1932, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 447, Box 489)
    This brief diary contains Ms. Walker's notes from interviews with professors and administrators at several top schools and institutes for social work primarily in the Southern and Western United States, dating between February 29 and December 30, 1932. Ms. Walker's provides the requests from the individuals seeking grant support from the Rockefeller Foundation as well as her professional recommendations concerning the schools and personnel involved. Walker includes details about the types of projects being pursued and the level of support they are already receiving.
  - 1933, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 466, Box 489)
    This brief diary contains Ms. Walker's notes from interviews with professors and administrators at several top schools and institutes for social work in the United States, dating between January 10 and December 29, 1933. Ms. Walker's provides the requests from the individuals seeking grant support from the Rockefeller Foundation as well as her professional recommendations concerning the schools and personnel involved. Walker includes details about the types of projects being pursued and the level of support they are already receiving, and this particular diary also references international social science programs being carried out in China and Australia.
  - 1934, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 498, Box 489)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between January 15 and December 31, 1934 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States, as well as mentioning programs underway in Europe and the Middle East with Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1935, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 534, Box 489)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between January 24 and November 15, 1935 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States receiving Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1936, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 554)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between January 14 and November 5, 1936 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. A large portion of Ms. Walker's diary is devoted to describing the status of the deposed German refugee scholars program and its progress in finding placements for German scholars in American universities. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects. One particularly prominent request in the diary is from McGill University in Montreal, which the Rockefeller Foundation had been providing significant support to since the early 1920s. The entry on McGill provides a noticeable contrast between a heavily Rockefeller-funded institution in Canada and other RF-funded institutions in the US and abroad in terms of the structure and method of social science research, as well as the fiscal responsibility of the university.
  - 1937, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 596)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between March 4 and December 17, 1937 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States and Europe receiving Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1938, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Reel M Wal 1, Frame 618, Box 489)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between February 1 and November 16, 1938 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States and Europe receiving Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1939, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 642)
    This brief diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between February 20 and November 20, 1939 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States, Europe, and Latin America receiving Rockefeller Foundation support. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, including refugee scholars seeking appointments outside of Europe, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
  - 1940, Walker, Sydnor Harbison (1891-1966) (Box 489, Reel M Wal 1, Frame 656)
    This diary records Ms. Walker's meetings and interviews between January 10 and September 5, 1940 with social science researchers and social work experts in the United States and abroad. Ms. Walker's diary references current social science programs in the United States and Latin America receiving Rockefeller Foundation support, and also alludes to changes in the RF's funding with regards to Europe as a result of World War II. Ms. Walker's diary is also a record of requests made for monetary support for social work and social science research projects, and provides details about the universities and institutions requesting support as well as the nature of their projects.
- Warren, Andrew J., 1.14 Cubic Feet 3 letter document boxes
  - 1930-1932 (Box 490)
  - 1933-1935 (Box 490)
  - 1936-1937 (Box 490)
  - 1938-1939 (Box 491)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 491)
  - 1942-1943 (Box 491)
  - 1944-1945 (Box 492)
  - 1946-1950 (Box 492)
  - 1951-1955 (Box 492)
- Washburn, Benjamin, 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
  Jamaica; West Indies; Central America
  - 1934-1936 (Box 493)
  - 1937-1939 (Box 493)
- Watson, Robert Briggs, 2.28 Cubic Feet 6 letter document boxes
  - 1946 (Box 494)
  - 1947 (Box 494)
  - 1948 (Box 494)
  - 1949 (Box 494)
  - 1950 January-June (Box 494)
  - 1950 July-December (Box 494)
  - 1951 (Box 494)
  - 1952 January-July (Box 495)
  - 1952 August-December (Box 495)
  - 1953 (Box 495)
  - 1954 (Box 495)
  - 1955 (Box 495)
  - 1956 (Box 496)
  - 1957 (Box 496)
  - 1958 (Box 496)
  - 1959 January-July (Box 496)
  - 1959 August-December (Box 496)
  - 1960 January-May (Box 496)
  - 1960 June-December (Box 496)
  - 1961 January-May (Box 497)
  - 1961 May-September (Box 497)
  - 1961 September-December (Box 497)
  - 1962 January-May (with Index) (Box 497)
  - 1962 June-December (Box 497)
  - 1962 January-June (Box 498)
  - 1962 June-December (Box 498)
  - 1963 January-June (Box 498)
  - 1963 July-December (Box 498)
  - 1964 (Box 499)
  - 1965 January-May (Box 499)
  - 1965 June-December (Box 499)
  - 1966 January-May (Box 499)
  - 1966 June-December (Box 499)
- Waugh, Robert K., 0.19 Cubic Feet 1 half-letter document box
  - 1959-1969 (Box 500)
- Weaver, Warren, 1.97 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes and 5 microfilm boxes (35mm)
  In his nearly three decades of leadership of the natural sciences at the Rockefeller Foundation (RF), Warren Weaver contributed substantially to the mid-century revolution in biology and agricultural science. Over a lifetime dedicated to building bridges across the sciences, he also contributed significantly to mathematics, statistics, physics, computer science, and scientific associations.
  Warren Weaver was born in Reedsburg, Wisconsin in 1894. He received his B.A. and Ph.D., as well as a Certificate of Engineering, from the University of Wisconsin. He served in the Army in World War I and taught mathematics at Throop College of Technology (now the California Institute of Technology) until 1920. Later that year, at the request of his mentor, physics professor Max Mason, Weaver joined the mathematics department at University of Wisconsin and chaired the department from 1928 – 1932. Together, in 1929, Mason and Weaver wrote the classic physics textbook, The Electromagnetic Field.
  In 1932, Mason, now president of the RF, persuaded Weaver to lead the Foundation's programs in natural sciences. Weaver's insight and intellectual risktaking led him to focus funding on scientific endeavors at early stages of development. With support from the Foundation, he developed a new program in experimental biology. At the same time, he identified opportunities for interdisciplinary work across the biological and physical sciences that resulted in the new field of molecular biology (which Weaver named).
  On leave to serve in the Air Force in World War II, Weaver organized the fire-control section of the National Defense Research Committee. A singularly important development, resulting from collaboration with Bell Telephone Laboratories, was the electrical antiaircraft device. Weaver then organized the Applied Mathematics Panel where interdisciplinary teams of mathematicians, economists and statisticians developed innovative techniques in sequential analysis and operations research.
  Having returned to the RF after the war, Weaver contributed to the development and expansion of the "Green Revolution" when agriculture was added to his portfolio in 1950. RF's agriculture programs not only supported breakthrough research on new, more productive varieties of corn, wheat and rice, they also contributed to training and institutional development, elements that Weaver knew were critical for ensuring long term success.
  In 1954, he became Vice President for Natural and Medical Sciences. Upon retiring from the RF five years later, he served as vice president of the Alfred P Sloan Foundation from 1959 to 1964 and trustee from 1956-1964.
  Outside his foundation work, Weaver served on the genetics panel for the National Academy of Sciences, authoring a pioneering report on the biological effects of radiation. He was elected a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Science in 1928 and president in 1954. He was also a trustee and board chair of the Salk Institute for Biological Studies.
  In 1963, his passion for probability led him to publish a book for the non-mathematical public, Lady Luck: The Theory of Probability. An aficionado of Lewis Carroll, Weaver published in 1964, Alice in Many Tongues, explaining the challenges of translating Alice in Wonderland into nearly 40 languages.
  In recognition of Warren Weaver's extraordinary contributions to the Rockefeller Foundation and to the pursuit of science, in 1989, the Foundation instituted the Warren Weaver Fellows Program. The fellows have been talented individuals who, during one-year residencies, have contributed fresh perspectives on the Foundation's work in specific program areas.
  Warren Weaver died in 1978 at the age of 84 in New Milford, Connecticut.
  - 1932-1959 (Travel Diary Index), Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 501, Reel M Wea 5, Frame 20)
    Travel Index; 107 pages; 1932-1959.
  - 1932-1958 (Summary of Foreign Travel by Country), Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture
    Summary of Foreign Travel by Country; 3 pages; 1932-1958.
  - Index, 1932; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
    Index; 11 pages; 1932.
  - 1932-1933, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978) (Box 501, Reel M Wea 1, Frame 1)
    The 1932 diary documents the Rockefeller Foundation Natural Sciences Division increased emphasis on support directed to special fields of interest in the form of general research grants to institutions and grants in aid of special research projects.
    Biology -- Research; United States
  - Index, 1933; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
    Index; 27 pages; 1933.
  - 1933, Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 501)
    The Rockefeller Foundation Natural Sciences Division focus from 1933 onward is biological sciences. Weaver tours various scientific laboratories and schools to assess for Rockefeller Foundation aid. The political situation in Germany is documented as well. The diary includes itinerary for trip to Europe May 3- June 13, 1933.
    Lithuania; Latvia; Physics; Norway; United States; Sweden; Poland; Austria; Zoology; Education; Estonia; Germany; Hungary; Biology -- Research; Chemistry; Croatia; Czechoslovakia
  - Index, 1934; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture
    Index; 19 pages; 1934.
  - 1934, Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Reel M Wea 1, Frame 2, Box 501)
    The focus of grant aid shifts from astronomy and meteorology to natural sciences. Weaver tours various universities to assess experimental biology interests and other Rockefeller Foundation Division of Natural Sciences program interests.
    Medicine; Interpersonal relations; Biology -- Research; Physiology; Sex
  - Index, 1935; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
    Index; 20 pages; 1935.
  - Index, 1936; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
    Index; 25 pages; 1936.
  - 1935-1936, Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Reel M Wea 1, Frame 3, Box 501)
    In 1935, the present Natural Sciences program of the Rockefeller Foundation is to assist in research related to understanding somatic behavior and aid is given to projects in experimental biology. Weaver interviews professionals in the field of natural sciences and tours universities and research facilities to assess Rockefeller Foundation programs in experimental biology. He tours Cambridge for new natural science research programs. The diary includes an itinerary for a European trip 1-27 May 1935.
    In 1936, The Rockefeller Foundation Natural Sciences program supports research in endocrinology, genetics and physiology to understand human behavior. The diary also documents fellowships.
    Genetics; England; Denmark; Botany; Biophysics; Biology -- Research; Agriculture; Sex; Plant hormones; Ireland; Immunogenetics; Holland (Netherlands: Province); Germany; Geophysics; United States; Sweden; Bergmann, M. (Max) (1886-1944)
  - Index, 1937; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences
    Index; 20 pages; 1937.
  - 1937, Weaver, Warren (1894-1978); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences (Box 502, Reel M Wea 1, Frame 4)
    The diary is arranged by interview and visit. Weaver discusses research interests and program issues with various professionals in the field of natural sciences. He tours American universities on behalf of the Rockefeller Foundation to assess experimental biology programs, interests and state of natural science education.
    Biology -- Research; Agriculture; Chemistry, Organic; Chemistry; United States; Physics; Mason, Max (1877-1961); Bohr, Niels, 1885-1962
  - Index, 1938; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Rockefeller Foundation. Natural Sciences and Agriculture; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978)
    Index; 17 pages; 1938.
  - 1938, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Natural Sciences; Weaver, Warren (1894-1978) (Box 502, Box M Wea 2, Frame 5)
    The focus of the Rockefeller Foundation Division of Natural Sciences is experimental biology. Aid is given to explore fundamental nature of various natural science fields. The diary also documents Weaver's trip to Europe and includes an itinerary 14-25 January 1938.